welcome back, everyone.
If you're just joining us.
Whether you are live with us
or you're joining on the stars repository,
thank you for being here.
My name is Petey Edgar,
and I'll be helping introduce and moderate
this panel on the periphery of Elit study
digital literary cultures,
plus featuring a number of presenters
who are going to speak together.
So I'll turn this over to Kira.
And welcome to everyone here.
And thanks for thanks for coming.
Yeah.
Thanks, everyone. So I'm Kira obert.
I am a
postdoctoral fellow
at the University of Waterloo, and
I am an adjunct professor there as well.
And what we're going to do today is
in test is just joined us.
So we will have everyone on the panel
just quickly introduce ourselves.
And then we're going to jump in and I'm
going to put some links in the chat.
So Camilla do you want to go
next on introducing yourself.
Yeah.
But shouldn't
you say a bit more about your research?
Kira I felt
that was a bit too short to short.
Okay, sure.
I study Instagram poetry
or I have studied Instagram poetry,
and now I'm kind of transitioning
into looking at more broadly
at women's literature throughout history
that has been denigrated or ignored
and also their associated publishing
technologies.
Thanks.
It's late for Camilla and I and I, so
we might need a little prodding.
And I always think,
I think it's nice to remind people
to be extra vocal about what they do,
especially I know Kira
and I think she know
she does so much cool stuff.
So I'm like,
please tell us more about yourself.
Yeah, but I'll go on.
And I think I'm also doing interesting
stuff.
At least I think so.
I'm currently a research librarian
and also met.
It's the Oslo Metropolitan
University of Norway and.
And the football match
is going on in the background here.
And Argentina just scored.
So in case you want to know that
but yeah, I might also the Metropolitan
University Norway.
I'm current chair of the National digital
humanities organization in Norway,
secretary of the Nordic Baltic
Digital Humanities Organization.
And I work at kind of the intersection
of digital humanities,
popular culture,
and especially digital popular culture.
I did my dissertation on platform
reception
of contemporary poetry,
and I've further gone on to research
public libraries and book talk,
doing a digital social
reading project with Kira
and our third colleague, Hannah Jorgensen.
And and I'm currently
also leading a project
at Region National Research Center
for AI and creativity on digitalization
and reintroduction and reuse of folk
historical craftwork in Norway.
So yeah, I think that sums up me
great.
Magdalena, do you want to go next?
Yes, I can go next.
So I'm Lena, as you as you've heard.
And so I also studied or study in poetry
because I'm still a PhD student,
but I'm really close to submission.
So yeah, this is an interesting time.
And I studied in support
as a poetic esthetic phenomenon.
And I think it is a reflection
of our current society.
And, and it's and that shows and it's
different esthetics like strands like
that's what my main point is of a post
digital side, guys that I see within it.
And I look at it from a feminist lens
that stands in high tension.
I think with the platform that happens.
So there is always this ambiguity
that is continuously there,
that that's what interests me.
I think the most.
And my approach
methodologically is like a multimodal
ethnography very broadly.
I've worked in the project
poetry in the Digital Age
at the University of Hamburg.
This is also where I'm a PhD student at.
And then I also did like
a couple
of months at the University of Vienna
in the project poetry of the page,
where I've previously studied
and where I came from,
and then moved to Germany.
So these are basically
like the two locations.
Yeah, that are important to me
in terms of research.
Yeah, this is a very, very short summary.
But yeah,
I hope you get something out of it.
Okay.
Thanks, Tanya.
Hi, everyone.
Can everyone hear me? All right.
Okay, great.
So my name is Tanya, and I'm currently
a postdoctoral fellow at Duke University.
And I'm also the co-investigator
on a shark knowledge
synthesis grant for the project
The Digital Life of the artist,
which belongs to one of sharks.
Future challenge areas.
Arts transformed I finished my PhD
and into the poetry in February 2025,
and currently I'm in the process
of revising my dissertation into a book
tentatively titled The Author
as Influencer, which traces the points
of tension and connection between authors
and influencers in the social media age.
It picks up my work on Insta poets
like Rupi Kaur, that considers
the rise of personal branding
as a kind of literary entrepreneurial,
but it also extends to other dimensions
of digital cultures
intersection with influencer economies.
It covers literary
IT girls like Caroline Kellaway,
immature writers on Substack,
and the growing celebrity of readers.
I'm also working on a computational
article about personalized user
generated Chandra tagging on Goodreads,
and I'm looking forward to incorporating
more computational methods
into my work as these go on.
Thanks.
And I will then ask
if you would introduce yourself.
Hi everyone!
Nice to nice to see you all
if I if I know you already
and nice to see some new names as well.
My name is Tess.
I am an assistant professor
of Digital Humanities and English
at the University of Illinois,
Urbana-Champaign.
I do work on a number of things right now.
My main project is a book project as well.
I'm currently
taking a break from agonizing over,
you know, every sentence
of the last draft of my book proposal.
So very,
very happy to put that aside for this.
The book, it's about major
general of viral content.
So what I've done is I've collected
large data
sets of most highly engaged content
in English language in U.S.
settings on five different platforms,
which are Facebook, Instagram, YouTube,
TikTok, Twitter or X,
and from 2010 to the present.
And I've sort of surveyed
this data for formal patterns,
and I've defined what I call like
five major general of viral content,
which are kind of broader.
They're not named like
the meme or cottage core
or things like that.
They're sort of broader formal structures
or tropes that I've defined that sort of
flow across platforms and across time
periods and across formats.
So it's sort of an esthetic and literary
take on viral content.
And so,
you know, in terms of thinking about the
the theme of this conference overall,
which is electronic literature,
I guess the way I describe my relation to
that is that
I'm really interested in the,
the popular media online
that does not explicitly call itself
literature or affiliate itself
with literature,
but is nonetheless literary and ascetic
and can be viewed through these lenses.
And so I'm really happy to be here.
And this is also my first time
participating in this conference, though
I've often admired it from afar.
And I have to say thank you
to the the organizers
for putting together
such a such a lovely program as well.
So the organizers of this panel
and also I was
I was totally enchanted with the
the program
the digital brings to the concept.
So thank you for that.
Anyway.
Yeah. Thanks.
Tess and Kim.
Hi everyone.
Thanks for having me.
And thanks for putting this together.
My name is Kim Martin.
I'm an associate professor in history
and culture and technology
studies at the University of Guelph,
where I think lab,
which is the Humanities Interdisciplinary
Collaboration lab with Susan Brown.
I worked with Chiara in the past and
in the future, I'm sure, on many things,
but my work doesn't
really touch on yellow materials,
so I'm really excited to be here
for the first time.
And my work kind of spans
and librarian information science.
So yeah, that would be really interesting
to see what comes out of this.
Great.
So the format that we're going to have
today is we're going to start with
some of us
speaking about this organization
called DLC
plus or Digital Literary Cultures Plus.
And then we're going to get into a brief
discussion of what we see
Elit and DLC
plus in conversation with each other.
And then Tess and Kim are advisory
board members on DLC plus,
and we're going to do a little fireside
chat with them to share some
some of what we've done as an organization
over the last year or so.
So I think what I'll do
is I'll just spotlight
the folks who are going to be speaking,
but I'll just hand it over to Tanya
and Camilla to get us started.
Okay, great.
So I'll start us off
and then I'll hand it over to Camilla.
Can everyone hear me? Okay,
great.
All right, so DLC plus digital
literary Cultures plus is first
and foremost and academic community.
And it's it's within community
that everything else emerges.
I think of DLC plus as a meaningful space,
where scholars of digital literature
and culture, including graduate students,
emerging scholars and established scholars
alike, can come together
and bring meaning
to the contemporary moment
by studying the narratives and texts
that are actively shaping our world,
and to do so through the humanistic
tradition of close reading,
even when those cultural objects
look a lot differently, a lot different
when we normally take seriously,
we provide the space through service.
So by maintaining a community on slack
where we chat informally and share links
and resources,
and by sending a newsletter,
but also through research
creation initiatives
like with our Keywords many conference
series, which seeks to pinpoint
the most pressing concept actively
shaping digital literary culture
like slop and smut that will eventually
make up a larger edited project.
So in that way, it's part resource, part
network, and part
ongoing collective public humanities
project grounded in community.
Most importantly, we're not just DLCs,
but we are a DLC plus,
and that plus is meant to capture
everything on the margins that is so new
and so rapidly evolving and emerging
that it often lacks an intellectual home,
as Insta poetry did,
which is what brought many of us together.
So Camilla and I met in 2020
at the reading into the Poetry Conference,
where we bonded over a shared approach
to into the poetry,
which included looking at it as a media
specific poetry
while retaining humanistic frameworks.
We did notice that most presenters
and all presentations were great,
but they were approaching the poetry
through the framework of traditional print
poetry, rather than looking at it
as a poetry that emerged from
and circulated across social media
and was unique to that environment.
The reality is the poetry is an amalgam.
When we only approach it through
the framework of traditional poetry,
it's destined to fail.
But like likewise,
when we only approach it
as an electronic medium,
we lose the other dimensions.
That means the poetry, like a spoken word.
Live performance and print histories
distinguish
Insta poetry
as a digital and analog medium.
In my experience, when I
started my PhD in 2019,
emphasizing the platform evoked questions.
Whether this was work was more
media studies as a discipline rooted in
communication studies, a social sciences
discipline rather than the humanities.
This is no longer the case.
The rhetoric of platforms has
thoroughly entered literary studies now,
but at the time there was not much room
for taking social media
seriously in the humanities.
Camilla and I co-founded DLC plus
because we wanted to create that space.
For that reason, DLC plus has resonated
particularly strongly with graduate
students and emerging scholars.
Even though we don't explicitly
label ourselves as a graduate student
or emerging scholars organization,
graduate students are so often
the ones willing to take risks
writing whole dissertations on topics
like Insta romantic and fanfiction
well before it becomes safe
or trendy to do so.
They often feel
like the plus in their departments
when they lack peers or mentors
working on their chosen area of study.
There were no experts
when we started researching the topic,
and while some scholars engaged in public
debate,
you gave it exactly
scholarly attention. DLC.
Plus, it's an intellectual home
that reminds
graduate students and emerging scholars
that you are indeed onto something.
And to look at all
the other people working on this
that you may not have otherwise met,
working alone in your department.
And more recently, as the years go
on, our community has welcomed more
and more established scholars as well,
and it has been a real privilege
to cultivate a space where scholars across
rank, institution, and geography
can come together in dialog.
And you can go out and.
So I was going to continue
saying that if you listen to Tonya,
it's very interesting what she says about
media studies
and going towards social science,
because even though we met
from my corner of the world,
media studies is seen as being part
of the humanities,
but it's seen as being at the opposite
end of the humanities.
And then you have literary studies
at the other end.
So for me, it was more about
how do I approach something
if I want to it
from the other side of the humanities?
So I was looking for people
who wanted to take that step.
And it's very interesting
how and I will come back to that, how,
you know, something like media
studies is somewhere in the world
seen as social science and another
part of the world seen as humanities,
but it also makes it kind of a perfect fit
for a way to approach Insta poetry,
as we did at that time.
And speaking further to
my own situated ness, I'm very.
So my whole research
and my way of thinking about things goes,
always goes back to Haraway
and further back to Harding.
Like how am I situated?
From where am I viewing something,
and how does that affect
how I know something and
the knowledge that I'm part of producing?
And I come from the tech humanities,
as it's called here in the Nordic.
So my go to is always like
hardware itself, where it's algorithms.
And at times I'm kind of like what you
would call like a dirty new materialist.
And I kept running into these hardcore
social sociologists here in the Nordics
who are all about
discussing culture and poetry by applying.
Berger.
And I didn't really find the production
and consumption
of culture
that interesting, at least not from the
duo's perspective.
Not at that time.
I now I, I see that he's applicable,
but I was more interested
in the distribution and circulation
and infrastructures and platforms
and understanding the socio technical.
So I was very much
a humanist in my pursuit,
but at the same time more oriented towards
pop culture, the collective contemporary
folk culture, social culture,
and not so much,
the ways that you found here
in like classical literary studies.
So I kind of missed the media
oriented literary studies for that reason.
That focused more on the network defects
of contemporary post digital culture.
And I wanted to share that interest
with other people,
or simply to find those people
who did work with this.
And that's out of this,
like I had that need.
And Tanya came
from a slightly different way,
and other people came from, you know,
other entrances, other situated in us,
but all with this interest in
how do we understand this new phenomenon.
So I guess that kind of
sums it up a bit
how DLC came about, doesn't it, Tanya?
Yeah, I think so, yeah.
So it also came.
It's also like it also came
from an online space, because that was
we met at an online conference
like in the middle of Covid.
Yeah.
Awesome.
Okay.
And I are now going to talk about
how we see
DLC plus.
Converging with or in conversation with
electronic literature
as a, as a broader field.
And I'm going to start us off there. So.
What I've been thinking about in a
and when I was thinking about putting
this panel together, I was thinking about
Leo Flores 2019 argument for this third
gen E literature,
defined as this writing centered art that
is, using these established platforms
with massive user
bases, right,
such as social media networks or apps.
ET cetera, etc.
and I was thinking about how Insta poetry
might fit into this,
this definition of the third gen of elit.
And at the time I.
Was so excited
to see in particular and Instagram
with legitimized
by such a prominent scholar of elit.
It was a very significant moment for me
in in particular, as we're all here,
scholars of digital literary culture
and many of us focus on instability.
Right?
But I was also very interested in elit
as a poet, myself, as a practitioner.
So to see those two worlds
colliding was very interesting.
So I've argued before that Insta poetry
in particular is part of third Gen Elit,
and I think this holds true, but
that there are some complications to it
as as we have continued
studying in support
and seeing different platforms
and different forms of literature
and writing evolve on this platform
and other platforms.
So I've been thinking about
and insert a lot lately,
and though there are defining elements
to insert poetry, I see value,
and I see value in categorizing in
as part of this, this third.
Jenny Lind I don't think that
the honor itself only exists on Instagram,
even though the current iterations of of
it are platform dependent.
Right?
But the question I'm asking more and more
is if social media platforms
are now all replicating each other
in terms of affordances
and what you can do on them in this race
for user attention,
then what's the difference between, say,
TikTok poetry and Instagram poetry?
How do we think of these things
differently or similarly?
So these ideas of start
to get really murky as we consider
Insta poetry as both a subgenre of elit
and part of a broader
digital literary culture as well.
And I think that these thoughts
and questions that I'm posing here
transitions
pretty nicely into my views on on lids.
Yeah.
So first of all,
I want to go back to instant poetry again
and say that there is not one in support.
That's why we
I think we have so many different scholars
and so many different perspectives on it.
And in my own research, I prefer to say
in supporting or in supporting artifacts.
So then rather than speaking
and talking about is this poetry or not?
Is this media artist, is post
internet art,
is this social media poetry and so on?
And also the
question
in traditional literally analysis,
maybe we can open up the discussion.
And I think in digital literary cultures,
plus this is very relevant and important
because otherwise
it would be difficult to come together
if we would think about it very narrowly.
So not only in terms of in support,
but coming from, in support
and then going into all different kinds of
directions of digital literary cultures.
Plus and that's where we meet,
so to say, in a readout network also.
So I think the organization
is also something that I always try to
yeah, not not maybe advertise,
but always tell people
when I meet them
and also do this in person.
So not only online.
And I think when you can relate to people
topically, it makes sense to talk about
the plus that we have
and what else is so to say there.
Because I think when meeting scholars,
they're not only scholars,
but as you also said, Kira,
they are also poets.
There are also organizes.
There was a teacher.
So they're also involved
not only in theory but also in practice.
And then we can maybe find a point to meet
and to also maybe discuss
then in the masterclasses.
Like what?
What does theory mean?
What does practice mean.
And then the whole question of it
may also come in
like what it means in practice as well.
So I think that yeah,
that's one of the point,
one of the points important
for the organization to
to really dive
into the scientific discussion
and to come together,
but also to acknowledge the ambiguity.
So I talked in the beginning
about the ambiguities that are there, that
tensions, and to pick that up and to
to maybe embrace that there, you know,
the boundaries are blurry or not.
Everything is so clear into. Yeah.
To pick up on that as a poets are also
not only poets but also visual artists.
And yeah, and maybe they don't even agree
with our terminological,
you know, work on in separately.
And there is also a tension there too.
So not only in the platform aspect
but also in that.
And as Kamila already said,
like the material specific point of view
comes comes into play there then,
and not only what we are doing right now,
because this is also a material specific
kind of conference,
which is also interesting.
But yeah, relating this praxis
back to the theory
and in teaching in support,
I think one of the aspects
that is important also for DLC
plus is the same place
where we have like AI slop
and where we talk about vibes
and talk about all these keywords
is also where in support we happens.
And that might have been
one of the reasons why it was rejected,
kind of in a scholarly realm,
but why it's so interesting, I think,
and why it can tell us so much about
what's happening in the world.
And yeah, not only about the media,
but in general about the culture
and and also what
what the poetry can do
and what poetry in literature is still so
still going back to the traditional,
but combining it with the platforms
and the media, specificity
from different perspectives. And
I think when we discuss this from,
from different points of view together,
we have a base of knowledge that we share.
And then you can really go in depth.
And that's, I think,
one of the strengths of the network.
And to really discuss like more
than, you know, surface level questions,
is it good or bad.
But, you know,
go deeper into into the matter.
And I think that's
really important to have.
And that's that's
also why
I joined the network in the beginning,
because I really wanted
to have discussions and not maybe explain
like what is Y2K or something,
you know, but
like go into the matter of yeah,
what in support is.
Yeah, yeah.
And what you've said there made me think
to like about blurriness of boundaries
and the complexity of the
of the poetry itself
and all the different elements of it,
is that when we're thinking about.
Electronic literature,
right, it's Insta poetry is electronic,
but it's also not.
It's it is print.
It is also live performance.
It is
then of course, also recorded performance
and like images uploaded to Instagram
and everything else.
But it is another area
in which we get those complications
and that blurring of a difficulty,
of lots of occasion and categorization.
Yeah.
And also thinking about, you know,
the accounting support is often defined
for its instantaneous
and this immediacy and,
and then what happens when it switches
to other material media
and does that disappear
and is it still in support or is it not.
Is it another type of.
Literary artifact
or whatever you want to call it,
depending on our perspective?
Yeah, yeah.
That's great.
I see a questions come in
just as we've been chatting.
Magdalena does a social media
aspect of Insta poetry also contribute
to traditional academic studies
rejecting the study of insta poetry?
I've seen some evidence for this.
If the social media part contributes
to the rejection of it.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, now not not so much anymore
because as would say,
as we said in the beginning.
But Tanya, like I also agree,
I graduate students try maybe out,
you know, different topics
and maybe don't even think so much
about being brave or but are just naive
and that's what interests you.
And you just start doing it.
And then you realize for time,
like how it's perceived and you know, what
the academic community is like
and so on.
And I think now it's more
so that I feel like it's picking up.
It's more of a trend.
But when you're on top of everything,
maybe you're already moving on.
So I think it's, you know, a movement
and it's not about who is first
or whatever,
but is there a genuine interest maybe.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think that's great.
Okay. Thanks. Thanks, Elena.
I'm going to switch us to our chat
with our advisory board members.
Unless you want to touch on anything else,
we have a few more minutes.
Okay, great.
So that's a little
bit for everyone here about what is what
we think of its connection to Elit so far.
And one of the things that we've done over
the last year is to create an advisory
board to help us grow this network
and professionalize a bit more.
And so we have McNulty and Kim
Martin here to chat with us and to share
their experiences on the advisory board
with us.
I'm going to just highlight
spotlight them and.
Nice and.
Thank you.
Okay, so we had prepared a few questions,
but I wondered
if there is any area in particular
that you wanted to start either of you
or if there's anything you want to respond
to in what we've said so far.
Yeah. Okay, cool.
That's fine.
So the question that we prepared are
what initially drew you to support
the plus and it's community of scholars.
And perhaps I'll pass it to kitten first.
Sure. Yeah. Thanks.
I think really
it was working with you in Think Lab,
and it was spring of 2024
when you came to me
and told me that there was a professor
at a local university,
shall we say,
who had basically announced that
insta poetry was really not studied.
And you were quite rightly furious,
and particularly
because I knew you were working
with all these other folks
and who had also been doing this work.
I thought, okay, well,
let's showcase this and do what we can.
And so we had a panel that was great
with the four co-leads here of Dlsu plus.
So they get to talk about their research
and kind of cement that yes, this is
this is a real thing.
And we've been doing it for a while now.
It blew my mind that one of you worked
at the same institution as this person.
And so I was yeah,
that was even more kind of shocking to me.
But it also really helped me realize,
because I knew Kira's work, it helped me
realize the kind of larger world
that the insta poetry was, you know,
taking place and in different ways
that it was being studied.
And so when I was approached
to be on the advisory board, it
just kind of made sense.
I wanted to help get your voices out
there.
And also, it's been a little while now
since I was a PhD
student, and I had lots of times
that I was frustrated and angry.
So if I can help relieve those for people
coming up behind me,
that's always useful.
Yeah, and thanks so much for that, Kim.
And yeah, I mean, so
I mean, first of all, you know, I'm
just so interested in this material.
I think it's so culturally important
right now and so central
to what's going on with literary culture.
So I was just, you know, excited
to see you all studying it.
And then, you know, I mean, the work
you guys are doing is amazing.
And also, I mean, as a as a plug
for this group and what they've done,
I mean, the organizing work they've done,
putting conferences together,
you know, you should all check out
some of these conferences
like you should attend them.
I've now attended one of the two
and it was amazing.
And the the level of participation,
the scope of participation,
the conversation.
So, you know, I could just tell they were
they were doing something really cool.
And I also think,
you know,
organizations like this,
that kind of work from the ground up
or how you make areas of study happen,
you know, just like with Instagram
Poetry itself,
you can't necessarily rely on,
like all of the gate keepers of the,
you know, the academic institutions
you're in to sort of
give the stamp of approval
to what you're doing.
So sometimes you have to
make your own structures and journals
and organizations and things like that.
So I just thought it was so cool
that you guys are doing that.
And then the final thing I'll say is that,
you know, I'm
so I'm an assistant professor.
I'm three years in.
So I'm not super advanced in my career.
But, you know, I have noticed
in the past couple of years
that, you know,
even when you sort of go to a conference
and, you know, you work on these sort of,
I mean, I don't really think studying
social media is marginal,
but I think studying it in a certain way
can be seen as marginal.
I think there's there's a trade off.
You're doing something
kind of new and trendy and desirable,
but you're also doing something
that a certain type of scholar
will kind of like, squint at and be like,
what is that, like a video game?
You know, like, so, you know, it's it's
you get it's a little bit of both.
Right.
But so, so I don't think it's,
you know, marginalized.
But, but I do think that there are spaces
where people are
just not going to be interested in it
and not take it seriously.
And so I've noticed sometimes
going to those spaces,
what's really galvanizing is that, like,
I might give a talk or something
and like the whole audience will be people
who are like younger than I am
or like at like the stage of career before
and or I guess after after me.
And so I just love
working with
any scholars who are even
just like the tiniest, the tiniest bit
last, you know, advanced in the profession
than I am because they're,
you know, interested in the stuff.
I'm interested.
Thing.
That's great.
Can you now share with us your experience
of advising the DLC
plus board of directors so far?
Like, what have you enjoyed?
What have you been part of?
And maybe test will start with you?
Sure, sure.
I mean, the you know, the conferences
you've put together
have just been so great
and it's just been really fun
watching the organization grow
from the ground up.
And, you know, from where it started to,
to where it is now,
like the amount of a sort of support
you've been able to assemble
and the events you've put on
are really great,
and I'm really looking forward
to seeing where you take it, which is,
you know, kind of maybe a segue into like,
you know,
some of the thoughts I was having
while these discussions were happening,
you know, about the the question
of traditional academic studies.
You know, it is an interesting moment
right now because so social media
is in a weird place, like social media
has become infrastructural.
So it's already becoming getting
that sense of kind of like obsolescence
that happens when when something becomes
an embedded infrastructure,
you know, like like email, you know,
everyone's not clamoring to study email,
you know, but like,
email is in the texture of our everyday
experience in this deeply embedded way.
So, you know, you know,
there's this rush now to study AI.
And it's like, that's the next wave.
And on the one hand,
this work is is really relevant to that.
You know, like I would love to see a study
of how Instagram poetry is like
playing into the training of these models
on sort of poetic writing.
You know, there's been some cool studies
on, you know, the poetry
that's composed
by, you know, GPT or Claude, etc.
and, you know, it rhymes too much.
It's sort of to classical
in its composition.
It's very rigid in its rules.
But, you know, if the if the training set
for a lot of this stuff involves
like common crawl and,
you know, upvoted posts on Reddit,
like there's got to be in poetry in there.
So I'm, you know, I'm curious about that.
So, so I'm interested to see
how on the one hand, this group
sort of will interface with new currents.
But on the other hand,
also seeing how it'll make a case
for the continued relevance of these,
these forms that that stay durable.
So, you know, like
I see this in my research all the time,
like everyone wants to hear about TikTok
and like I'll talk about TikTok.
But Facebook still has two
thirds of American adults
as self-reported users, and TikTok
has really just edged about one third.
So like, you know, just because something
is not buzzy and trendy,
it can still be much more part of, like,
the fabric of ordinary digital experience
than these kind of rapidly
moving cultural conversations suggests.
So I think it'll be
really interesting to see how
how you
all move forward with kind of navigating
like what social media sort of represents
right now in the culture.
And yeah, being a scholar,
even at my level now, it's like I'm
so I'm an assistant professor.
So I'm like moving into the first wave
of being like,
oh, like I'm like moving
moving past the undergrads.
Like I'm not in touch with them
culturally.
More like all of these things.
I'm like,
how do I deal with, like, my own,
my own sort of
aging in terms
of the culture, so,
or some aspects of the culture.
So anyway, yeah, for sure.
It's such an interesting thing to
to think about, you know,
what's coming next,
but also what's actually lasting.
And I was thinking about this with Tonya's
project on Goodreads.
Right.
So like Goodreads is still going strong.
It's not like the fancy new story
graphs or what
have you,
but it is still something that it's,
a key component of
digital literary culture
and reader communities, right?
Yeah.
Ken, what about you?
Well, first, Tess,
if you want to stay in touch
with what's happening,
you have a child like me
who's going to university this year,
and then he tells you
how old you are all the time.
It's a great feeling.
Let me tell you.
Yeah.
On the advisory board,
I mostly have been involved with meetings
around these kind of mini conferences
that you've put on,
and I want to speak
to the first one in particular,
because it was such a great online
conference for a variety of reasons.
So this is the one that the two keywords
were smut and law,
and it was a half day event,
which is the like
most lovely kind of online event,
because I really cannot do
kind of 3 or 4 days
of continuously staring at my screen
and trying to keep things in.
It's it's quite difficult.
And those two keywords kind of played off
each other really nicely.
And having the keywords
allowed the different disciplines
of all the speakers to kind of come
together around these terms.
And I remember for the law,
which was the first half,
I believe there were talks on like LMS,
fantasy Fiction and education.
The three like things that you would not
normally put together in any way, shape
or form, all kind of coming together
through this keyword.
And each speaker presented
their own definition of the term,
which is a really nice way
to kind of set off.
This is what I think,
and this is where I'm going.
But then in both of the conversations they
like, the conversation followed.
They talked about each
other's definitions. Right?
So they engaged with each other
across disciplines.
And then when it came to smut,
the first two
speakers talked about kind of reclaiming
that term as scholarly
and talking about how to take a like
ethics of care approach, doing that work.
And then the second two speakers
really did this wonderful job of showing
how they put that into practice by looking
at Taylor Swift and romance novels.
Right.
Two things, again,
that were really kind of wide ranging
but fascinating, both great talks.
And I think by putting
these kind of things together in duos
and by having just this half day
event online, you all were like
really careful about pushing back
against kind of the academic norms
of like day long 3 or 5
to 3 to 5 sessions, like really, you know,
expecting to kind of be in the room
and you were so welcoming of speakers.
I, I'm like hyper attentive to everyone
getting a question
at any kind of conference.
Like, everyone who gives a talk
should get a question.
And so I'm usually like madly
writing these things down
to make sure I can do that.
And this was the first time
I've never had to do it
because everyone involved in DLC
plus was ready there with questions.
And just like, so deeply engaged.
And at the end of it,
I thought, I'm going to write a blog post
on how lovely this is.
And then my life
just continues to fall apart, so I didn't.
But now I've said and verbalized
how wonderful I thought it was.
So yeah, it's great to be a part of it.
I didn't make it to the second one,
but I'm really excited for more of those
to happen and to keep thinking
about how we build on them.
Yeah, thanks.
Yeah, I think getting that feedback
from our advisory board
to have these mini conferences
and to really focus them in this
so important and instrumental
to the success of those conferences.
Did any Camilla may delay?
Tanya, any of you want to jump in or say
anything about the mini conferences?
I guess I could just add that
it's it's sort of a solution to
kind of a challenge of like building
a true international research network
because we are very international, like
Magdalena is in Germany, I'm in Norway,
and Kira is not in Canada
at the moment, but that just shows
how international we are, right?
You are in,
in a country in Europe.
That's right.
In Kosovo.
And to have this sort of mini
conference is a much
it's a way to hopefully
bring in more people.
And we struggled a bit with wanting to do
like very like, you know, on
set physical conferences or meanings.
But is there any hard
when you're like that international
and especially like the infrastructure
as a research
are surprisingly very national
or regional like?
For me, it's
very easy to set up a mini conference
at the Nordic Baltic Digital Humanities
Yearly Conference on this theme, but
then that would make it hard
for people outside of Europe to travel
or feel included to come.
Right.
And I'm also an editor of the Nordic
Baltic Digital Humanities Journal,
and we could always do a special edition,
but that would require publishing
an edition or having a special edition
with relations to the Nordic Baltic,
which wouldn't make sense
because we are more than Nordic.
But I'm the yeah, we're only yeah,
we're just a couple of Nordic people,
so that would just not make sense
at all. So
like creating like these meaning spaces.
It's just
you need to do it digitally, even if it's.
And then as been said, it's like, oh,
it can be very draining
to watch your screen.
So having these short ones.
Yeah.
It's a, it's a, it's the best solution
I guess.
Yeah. It's very light here.
So sorry for my rambling.
Yeah.
But I think you've
teed us up
for our final question for our panelists.
Oh Tonya, go ahead.
Yeah, I wanted to actually add on to that.
So I think the international structure,
although it is like a challenge,
I think it actually
really suits the material well because
like a lot like literary studies,
I know we don't all
like not everyone's going to approach.
Right.
Like this poem as a literary object,
I do, but.
Right.
It's not really an object
that's going to be evaluated
according to like, Canadian literature.
Like I try to study it
within the context of Canadian literature.
My dissertation, and it was like not
coming together because it is like viral.
It's surpassing continents,
like everyone's watching and liking it.
So like the fact
that we were able to come together,
I think it was like a natural product of
like what we study.
And this organization,
I think can really help
kind of bring people together
even when they're not located,
not only in the same
university, but like in the same country
or like continent.
Yeah, I need to finish that
thought, Tanya, because it's like our like
situated ness, like we're all situated,
we all have partial knowledge.
And there's examples that I can think of
right now, like,
for instance, when we were coming together
with Insta poetry,
a lot of people I met
from like US and Canada were like,
oh, it's like feminist study.
It's it's all about these women
who are posting poetry.
And in Norway I was like,
this doesn't make sense.
It's only men doing poetry here in Norway.
Like, why would you study this
from a feminist angle?
Right?
Because we had different experiences
of this phenomenon.
And now working with Book Talk
with Chiara and Hannah Jorgensen from us,
I also keep running into like,
oh, this is so strange.
And then it's like,
oh, this is very common in the US.
And I'm like, oh, oh, okay.
So it's not strange.
Yeah. It's just like American culture.
I find American
culture very fascinating and.
Yeah,
if I can add
to that, I don't know if the time allows.
Yeah. Go ahead.
Yeah.
And also I just wanted to add
also different languages because Camilla
also Norwegian
and in my case also German and Polish.
And what that means for the studies
I think is also relevant.
And also how
because you mentioned feminism,
how it connects to,
to feminist movements like feminist
activism and how in support is connected
there in some niches and for example,
in Poland, that's the case.
So then again,
we have this tension as I've talked about,
and I think you can see this very well
also in the cultural differences.
But in the end it's still matter.
And it's still yeah, you know,
this tech US conglomerate,
even though we have a bit of different
laws here in the, in Europe.
So I think that's also interesting
to study,
like what is allowed in terms of data
and how is the Digital Services
Act implemented
and what kind of political content
and social content is shadow banned
and is made less visible or more visible?
I think that's also regionally
and nationally different,
and that's also very interesting.
I think in terms of study, interesting
or sometimes really bad or horrible,
and at times you didn't understand
what happens there.
Yeah.
What happens on the platforms
and what happens with the actual social
and political content
and also in, in support,
but not only in, in supporter yet.
So that's what I wanted to add.
Thanks.
I think we've kind of gone through
a lot of the other questions that we had
for our advisory board members, but
I wondered if quickly, Kim,
you wanted to talk
about what you've learned from this role
and how you would.
Suggest to other,
more senior scholars
how to best support emerging researchers
and these sort of emerging networks
like you have with DLC plus?
And Kim,
I was like, you better choose
because we're both thinking, yeah.
Yeah, this is the hard one.
The questions you had listed, I was like,
I mean, I can think of a lot of ways
that I think would be useful,
but really the, you know,
it really comes down to what you need.
And you're all at like
slightly different points in your career.
And I'm always happy to like,
chat about things that you want to do,
but it is something quite different
that you've created.
So like, I don't want to necessarily say,
you know, does this or in Lis we do this
like I like to I guess my suggestion
would be like keep it unique.
And and you know, I think it's nice
that it's a community
based thing as opposed to a academic like,
truly like academic network
that you pay me things into.
And that's, that's a different,
whole different vibe. Right.
And a lot of that comes
from what it is you're studying,
I think.
Probably the,
the, I guess my biggest like
word of caution is you're all going
to be doing so much all the time.
You're all already doing so much
all the time.
People are going to tell you
it gets better. It doesn't.
You just keep doing more.
So you have to think about where this fits
into all of the things
that you're going to do as you keep going
forward with your books and your careers.
And, you know,
I think one of the maybe best advice
is try to find people
that are junior to you
in a couple of years and invite them in,
and so that if you move on, it doesn't die
and you don't feel like,
oh gosh, this is the thing that I have to
move forward forever
and ever and ever. So.
Yeah, thanks.
That's yeah, I totally I agree with that.
I mean, in a way,
when you ask your question like what?
What have I learned?
I also had trouble with this one
because, you know,
even though a sensibly an advisor
and I will always happy to weigh in on, on
anything you all do and give opinions,
it's really just more been like
being a fly on the wall,
like watching you build this.
Cool.
You know, so
it's just been been fun
to, to watch and be a part of it.
And I was on, you know, honored to
to be asked to give, give feedback.
But, you know, you've already
just put on such, such cool events.
And I totally agree, you know,
finding a kind of like,
you know, strategy for,
for passing it on as well, you know,
when you have more things to do. But
yeah, it's just
been, it's just been cool to watch.
Thank you.
I know we have all benefited so much from
having the input of the advisory board.
So I want to thank you both
for being part of that too.
Well, it did you want to say something?
Oh, I just wanted to nod, but yeah.
Okay. Okay.
I think I actually accidentally
unmuted myself
to not so. Yes.
30. Yeah.
You know, it's it's very late for us,
so I get it.
Yeah.
Okay.
So we've got about ten minutes left
and I just wanted to open it up.
Now for any questions from the audience.
Or comments are also encouraged.
Yeah. Jason.
Yeah.
So so you're here
at the Electronic Organization conference
and you're speaking to members
of the Electronic Literature organization.
And so I think a lot of us
would be really interested
to hear your thoughts about what
the connections
between the ELO and the DLC
plus are, because I see a lot of overlap,
if not potential replication
happening here.
And so I'm really interested to
know, like you saw the ELO,
what was the yellow not doing
that prompted you to say
we need the DLC plus,
and how much you think
about working with the ELO
going forward?
So I think what distinguishes DLC plus is
that like we're
also for example,
like not just focused
on the electronic medium.
So we might be studying
like digital culture
as is represented in a novel
as it's on film.
So there is like a much bigger emphasis on
like not just the electronic medium
versus like poetry,
like I like my research.
And poetry also encompasses
looking at live performance,
and the visual.
So I think that's sort of
what distinguishes DLC plus.
And I also would say that it is really
geared toward or it's not geared toward,
but it really tries to make space
for emerging scholars.
I think that's part of
like the mission statement.
But I would I think it would
be great to keep to work with ELO
in the future and to develop
like some kind of ship
would be a wonderful
I could I can also add to that
that I actually started out in the yellow,
and I think DLC was kind of
out of respect for ELO,
because I've been very much like
my background
has been very much about,
very media specific
literature
all the way back to my master studies.
And, but I felt like I was going in a way,
and I was studying something
that wasn't really like the connection
it had to
a medium was more social media
as a distributional medium for poetry.
And that was kind of and it felt like
if we're also going to like start putting
that into ELO,
it kind of will like make Elo too big
because
yellow is should be more focused
on the actual,
cultural artifacts
that are specifically media sensitive
and have have thought
through the use of media in some way.
And for instance, for
I feel like we always
go back to the poetry here
and now it's for me, it's like two,
two years since I researched it. But,
one of like my contributions back
then was the post
digital distribution process of poetry,
where I showed
how little
poetry or contemporary poetry
or Insta poetry
actually was related to Instagram.
It's just used Instagram
as a way to distribute
the things that were actually happening
in our, like,
meatspace or physical world or real world
or whatever you want to call it.
And that was the connection.
And so it was more about like,
where do you find the
space, where it's more about
the digital
being, distributional and network places
for connection around objects
that are not necessarily
or could be defined as electronic media.
Yeah, yeah.
And I think it's, I think to when we were
we're all starting off with our research.
Like if you think of the previous
or earlier generations of elit,
there was a more of a focus on difficulty.
Right.
And we don't find that as much
with Instagram poetry,
certainly not in the same ways.
And so prior to,
you know, that 2019 article
that I referenced on third Gen,
we didn't really see
I didn't see much of a place
for Instagram poetry within Elit.
So I think that would be my impetus
for coming to here.
And I think that's
largely because it's it's not
difficult in the ways that like, hypertext
fiction is.
Right.
Can I speak to that?
I, I'm
so excited about about you being here.
I'm former
president of yellow for two, two terms.
Right.
So the way I define electronic literature
to people who are complete newbies
to the world is it's participatory,
interactive and experientially.
So I call it pi.
That makes it a lot of sense like that.
So it's a big it's a big category, right?
It's a big series of categories
that people
know that when Leo was president
he funded the journal filter.
So funded filter, which is Instagram.
Right. And that Sarah Lola's work.
And so we have always taken a big tent
approach to electronic literature.
In fact, when we were founded,
there was a great deal of discussion.
I call it discussion
about what to call ourselves, because
people were coming out of hypertext,
and Scott was insistent upon the idea
that we should not limit ourselves
to hypertext, because in 1999,
there's a lot of other stuff happening.
So I think that you're
in the perfect environment to gather more
people interested in your work
and to find some friends.
And it's great for you to be here
because you fit well with us.
So welcome.
Yeah.
And also,
I just noticed that Dan made comment
in the
in the chat that I also wanted to ask.
And that is preservation.
That's that's an area
that I'm interested in.
So as you're working on your projects,
please be thinking about
how you're going to hold on to this
because it's really hard
to hold on to social media.
It is. Yeah.
And it's complicated
in terms of copyright as well. And
yeah, like the user
terms of Instagram
and other platforms as well.
But yeah, it is a big a big issue,
a big question.
I'm trying to get access to the face
to to meta and all of their data
for Facebook, for Jumpy or Bob's
Facebook posts for his exhibition.
We did this past year
and I couldn't get access.
They would not let us
have have access to it for art purposes.
Right?
Yeah, yeah, it's proprietary information.
And I do just want to say that
I don't think that it's that we don't see
Instagram poetry as fitting in with.
We do think that it is a form of it.
It's just that DLC plus goes beyond that.
And we've talked a lot about Insta poetry,
but DLC plus is more than that.
And it's also not always stuff
that's like hugely literary
can be more on the digital side
than the literary side sometimes too.
One more thing is interesting.
I'm sitting in,
I don't know if you see my lab,
but I'm here surrounded by my computers,
and I was in this room
when the MIT press sent me an email
and asked me to review a book by someone
who was writing a book about paper.
And the argument was that people
in electronic literature community
don't like paper.
We don't use paper, anti paper.
And in this room we're 100 boxes of papers
that artists had produced
in conjunction with their work.
And then we also have ephemera
and all kinds of them sit there.
And I wrote back and I said,
you don't want me reviewing this book.
You know, me reviewing this book
because we we are not anti paper.
The notebooks that Deena Larsen has in her
collection
are vital to understanding
how Deena created her work.
So, Deena, I know you're in the room.
So just saying.
So it's a really interesting thing.
People think of us as strictly computer
based
or digital based,
but we're so broad, it's bizarre.
And so.
Yeah. So welcome.
Thank you for being here.
Yeah, yeah. Thanks.
Thank you all
so much for a wonderful panel.
I think we've just hit our time marker,
but I wanted to say thank you all for
for putting this together.
I think DLC plus exists interstitial
and interdisciplinary
and a very similar way to yellow.
And so I'm really excited to continue
working together with you
all moving forward.
It's this has been a really cool
discussion.
Thank you everybody.